You've probably seen this ad, though
maybe not by choice. Grubhub was the
biggest delivery app, 70% market share.
They had total dominance, but now that's
less than 10%. It had a $2 billion IPO,
then it was acquired for 7.3 billion,
but then sold off for less than 1/10 of
that.
No one is using Grubhub. What the heck
happened?
Delivery apps like DoorDash and Uber
Eats launched around 2013 and 2014, but
Grubhub was actually a decade earlier
and it really was the first to solve the
delivery problem. Imagine a world about
20 years ago with no DoorDash, no
Grubhub, no food delivery apps at all.
If you wanted to take out, you had to
take through a stack of paper menus,
call a restaurant, make your order, and
sometimes read out your card details.
Two developers, Matt Maloney and Mike
Evans, were sick of this. We were
frustrated by the lack of dinner options
as well as the pain in the ass of
calling restaurants and reading our
credit cards. At the time, we were
working on geographic lookup searches
for rental real estate. That's when I
heard at the screeching wheels in my
head. Why wasn't there something like
this for food delivery? So, they started
Grubhub, an online menu, but they needed
restaurants. The two went door-to-door
across Chicago collecting paper menus
and building a database, but there was a
problem. Around this time in 2004,
websites weren't that great and many
restaurants already tried having one,
some spending thousands, and it usually
didn't pay off. Matt and Mike's price
point, $140 for 6 months placement,
wasn't that appealing. So, they tried
something else. We said, "What if we
take a 10% commission on whatever we
sell for you?"
Restaurants loved that.
The change worked, but there were two
problems.
First, no one wanted to invest. It was a
weird business model with a weirder
revenue model. The other problem was
awareness. Luckily, Matt and Mike knew
how to reach their market because they
knew Chicago. People leave work right
before dinner and are hungry and
susceptible to Grubhub's marketing. So,
they advertised at the bustling Chicago
transit hubs. Plus, there were other
perks. We noticed that the person
managing the outdoor ads was really bad
at taking them down. So, we knew that if
we bought a month of space, we'd get
five. Grubhub quickly took off in
Chicago. Orders began flooding in.
They expanded to San Francisco with
their own bootstrapped funding. Within 2
years, they won the University of
Chicago Booth New Venture Challenge. In
2007, they raised their Series A, 1.1
million. By 2010, Grubhub was operating
in 14 cities on just $3 million in
outside capital. And then came the real
investment. $31 million.
That was nothing compared to what was
coming. Though first, yet another
problem. Grubhub was exploding, but they
weren't alone.
Other delivery websites were appearing,
and one in particular was Seamless.
They were doing the same thing, but with
a firm grip on one of the most lucrative
markets, New York. A dense urban
population, thousands of restaurants,
the delivery app dream.
The companies were similar. We were
solving the same problems, but in
different geographies. Seamless
consistently made a very smart decisions
both with product and the
If Grubhub could have just get maybe 10%
of New York's delivery market, the
commission revenue would be huge.
Though, it would be a tough battle. So,
Grubhub did something else.
In 2013, Grubhub and Seamless merged.
Grubhub was doing a really good job
nationwide, but Seamless had incredible
brand awareness in New York. It's like a
religion there.
By keeping both brands, we didn't have
to spend money to promote Seamless in
markets outside of New York or to
promote Grubhub inside New York. Best of
both worlds, right? Grubhub was on a
roll and that momentum carried them to
an IPO in 2014, a $2 billion valuation
which raised 200 million.
Everything was going great for now. In
the background, two different
competitors prepared for war.
Grubhub might have paved the way for
food delivery, but these new apps were
going to be different.
Let's say you've got a contact form on
your site. Someone fills it in. You want
it to ping you on Slack, save their
details somewhere, send them a
confirmation. Normally, that means
spinning up a server, faffing about with
endpoints, sorting out hosting. A bit
much for a contact form, isn't it? I use
Make for this kind of thing and this
video is sponsored by them. Set up a
webhook, connected to Slack, a Google
Sheet, and a Gmail for a confirmation
email. Now, Make does it automatically.
Done. Took about 5 minutes to set up.
Make is great for automation from a
simple back end like this to pretty
advanced automations. They call it the
Make grid. You can see the whole thing
laid out. If it breaks, you look at the
canvas and spot the problem in about 3
seconds. No hunting through logs. You've
got over 3,000 apps to connect and many,
many templates you can start using
immediately. Connect leading Facebook
ads with Google Sheets. Have Telegram
files automatically uploaded to Google
Drive. Auto apply to Instagram comments
or set up an automated AI analysis of
Google Analytics. You can even build
full AI agents directly on the same
canvas. If it breaks, you look at the
canvas and spot the problem in about 3
seconds. No hunting through logs. Click
the link in the description for a free
month of Pro. 10,000 operations
included. Thank you to Make for
sponsoring this video. In 2013 and 2014,
both DoorDash and Uber went live. And
unlike Grubhub, they offered something
extra. Delivery. Their own network of
delivery drivers.
Grubhub originally was just an online
menu or more a marketplace for
restaurants. It was up to those
restaurants to handle delivery. If they
didn't, too bad. And this model left a
huge gap in the market. Unlike Grubhub,
DoorDash delivered from almost any
restaurant, even those that had never
offered delivery before. They handled
the logistics, organization, scheduling,
payment, and everything else. The
drivers just came to the restaurant. So,
any mom-and-pop business could suddenly
deliver. DoorDash built its own network
of drivers known as Dashers. In fact,
the founders delivered the first 200
orders themselves just to figure out the
logistics. DoorDash and Uber immediately
had a way more options for customers.
But, it also came at a cost, which Matt
and Mike were very aware of. To make it
work, it was a sort of lose-lose
scenario. A small cut of commission for
restaurants, low pay for drivers, and
they somehow had to figure out how to
make all of this profitable. Matt
Maloney didn't like this. Even though
they said they were profitable, Matt
called them liars. People are going to
look around and say,
"Oh, crap. I can only do this for 12
months, even if I just raised a hundred
million, because every incremental
transaction is negative." Matt hated
this business model. You have to recruit
people, you have to train them, you have
to get them on a schedule. And by the
way, you have to do it without telling
them what to do because of the legal
implications. The logistics business is
crummy. It has bad margins. The only
thing that matters here is volume of
orders. To be fair, he's not wrong.
These companies were losing lots of
money and their margins were awful. They
were soaking up billions. In 2016, Uber
lost 2.8 billion, then 4.5 billion in
2017, and the losses continued for
years. Grubhub, on the other hand, was
very profitable. But now, they had to
change something or they'd be left
behind. Investors saw the writing on the
wall. If they didn't adapt, they'd be
dead. So, in early 2015, Grubhub
acquired two delivery companies, Dining
In and Restaurants on the Run. Grubhub
had to adjust its financial approach
from making great profit to just staying
afloat to keep up with DoorDash and Uber
Eats. "I'm running my delivery-based
business with the explicit goal to break
even. That's not fun for me and normally
I'd say that's the dumbest you could
ever be in. Why run a break-even
business? That's a pain in the butt."
Grubhub's marketplace margins were as
high as 35%, but
not anymore. Plus, to stay profitable,
Grubhub did two things: charge the
customer or charge the restaurant.
Grubhub is doing both, grabbing an
additional 10% from each order and
attaching on a customer delivery fee of
around $2. That's barely enough to cover
the costs in an ideal scenario. And why
Maloney thinks DoorDash and Postmates,
which have to make those numbers work at
a fraction of Grubhub scale, have no
hope of ever reaching profitability.
But, unfortunately, even if this might
have been responsible and smart, it
would cost them. These companies weren't
even really focused on profitability, at
least anytime soon. They were focused on
scale and growth. After 2016, Grubhub
began losing market share, while
DoorDash and Uber Eats grew rapidly.
Uber Eats in dense urban cities, and
DoorDash in suburbs, and in particular,
California. But, not all hope was lost.
Grubhub was still massive and had
attracted a different type of customer.
Grubhub was shrinking, but we're still
growing. We're trying to get to 1
million subscribers. So, please help us
out and click the subscribe button.
Grubhub's dominance fell from nearly 70%
of market share at its peak to around a
34% by 2018, and just 10% by 2021.
Smaller than Uber Eats, way behind
DoorDash. The tables were turned, which
brings us back to Uber. In May 2020,
Uber approached Grubhub with an offer.
>> There was a time last year when VC was
investing in this in private markets,
and they really loved this whole theme.
They like it much less now. They don't
like it in part of Uber, either. So, I'm
not really sure about what sort of
scenarios I haven't given it a whole
heck of a lot of thought where you put
some combinations together, and the two
pieces together are worth more than what
they are right now. We've seen a lot of
>> But, something unexpected happened.
Another company jumped in. Not a
DoorDash, but a company called it Just
Eat Takeaway, a European giant. Why all
these sudden interest in Grubhub?
Simple. This was early 2020. The
pandemic had hit. Home delivery was at
an all-time high. Grubhub's revenue
jumped from 1.3 billion in 2019 to over
2 billion in 2020, then to 2.3 billion
in 2021. Grubhub users also grew from 22
million to 31 million. Just Eat was
looking to break into the US market
during the pandemic. In June 2020, it
struck a 7.3 billion-dollar all-stock
deal to acquire Grubhub. Unfortunately
for Just Eat, they had just bought the
peak and were about to sell the bottom.
In the meantime though, internal tension
was rising. The deal closed in June 2021
and the leadership clashed over
strategy, particularly between Matt
Maloney and Just Eat Takeaway CEO, Jitse
Groen. They couldn't agree on where
Grubhub should go. So, 4 months later,
Maloney was gone. And now, Grubhub had
bigger problems. As the pandemic ended,
restaurants reopened, bringing down the
inflated delivery numbers.
Grubhub's decline accelerated. They were
already at 18% market share in 2020 and
it only got worse. The pandemic really
established the winners and the losers
of delivery. No one wanted to use
Grubhub. Investors realized Just Eat
vastly overpaid for Grubhub. CatRock
Capital, a Just Eat investor, publicly
urged shareholders to push back against
Just Eat's leadership. We believe the
bulk of the value destruction occurred
because Just Eat management gave
investors a misleading financial outlook
in advance of the two Grubhub
shareholder votes, leading to two
massive profit downgrades in 2021 and
shattering investor trust in management.
For context, CatRock owns 14.8 million
shares in Just Eat. It was bad and they
weren't wrong to be angry. In early
2021, JET disclosed that its profit had
disappeared and its EBITDA was expected
to be a loss of 64 million to 85
million, Catrock said. Even worse, Just
Eat was doing fantastic but a Grubhub
was doing so badly it was dragging Just
Eat down with it. Grubhub's value
collapsed forcing a 3.1 billion dollar
write down. By late 2024, the gap was
clear. DoorDash held a 47% of long-term
customers, Uber Eats had a 29% Grubhub
was left with just 11% and now Just Eat
was trying to get rid of Grubhub but it
wasn't easy. As profit margins
disappeared, debt climbed past 500
million. Just Eat spent more than two
years searching for a buyer. Eventually,
an offer came in 2024 from Wonder Group
for just 650 million dollars down from
the original 7.3 billion dollar deal.
And because of the debt, Just Eat
Takeaway walked away with a mere 50
million dollars.
So, why did a Grubhub lose? In my
opinion, Grubhub lost because they were
right. DoorDash lost money on every
single order from founding until 2024.
Matt correctly identified it that
delivery was a race to the bottom.
DoorDash and Uber Eats were burning
hundreds of millions subsidizing cheap
deliveries and the low fees to grab
market share. These companies were
effectively paying customers to use them
while Grubhub tried to stay disciplined
and maintain margins. The same or
similar restaurant but on one app, it's
$4 cheaper. Of course, customers will
use it. By the time DoorDash and Uber
Eats were actually thinking about
profit, they'd already won and that
really is the sad part. I actually have
respect for Matt out of all of this.
Delivery apps aren't the most noble
business and at least he tried to make
it work the right way and made it clear
he didn't like the new low margin
business. The way most of them work,
everyone loses. Low delivery pay, high
restaurant commissions and even the
companies weren't even making money.
Unfortunately, markets don't always go
where the best margins are. Grubhub
definitely deserved all of this for that
terrible ad though. Weirdly enough, all
that effort to take ground by Uber might
not even be enough. Uber is now
profitable but this company needed tens
of billions to get there and investors
aren't even that impressed with the
results. Was all of this even worth it?
Click here to learn the rest of the
story but until then, I'm Harry and I'll
see you guys on the next one.